Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Ships and Shipping Records 1660-1943 MS 563
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
- Schooner Regulator, 1799, 1807 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Alien Passenger List on Board Schooner Regulator, Master James Allen, arrived at port of New York from Jamaica (1799). Account of Master Richard Adams of Schooner Regulator (1807).
- Brig. Reuben & Eliza. Oversize, 1822 (Box Oversize - Small, Folder -)
  Brig Reuben & Eliza's Passport. Certificate that Brig Reuben & Eliza (of New York), Charles Harris, master, has no guns and may pass, owned by citizens of the United States. Contains Presidential signature. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman, 22 November 1924.)
- Boat Revenue, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  Receipt of articles shipped on board Boat Revenue of the Fultonville and NY Canal Line.
- Sloop Richard Alfred, 1805 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Particulars of the Capture of Sloop Richard Alfred by Privateer Schooner under French Colors sailing from New Providence bound for New York. (Gift from John Neafie, 29 March 1922.)
- Sloop Rising Sun, 1797 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Bill of Lading; Thomas Davenport, Master of Sloop Rising Sun.
- Convoy of the Roman Emperor, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  Signals and Signal flags to be observed by the convoy of the Roman Emperor. (Gift of Graham Brush, care of City Bank & Farmers Trust Co., 21 March 1939.)
- Steamer Rosedale, 1919, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  Correspondence regarding the Matter of Satisfactory Reimbursement for Governmental Takeover of Steamer Rosedale. Correspondents include Acting Secretary of the Navy Franklin D. Roosevelt, William J. Fredericks, John R. Westwood, George P. Darrow, and Josephus Daniels. Contains Presidential signature.
- Sloop Royal Charlotte, 1779 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  Robert White, Master of Royal Charlotte, or in case of death, Daniel Stuvant, or in case of death, Alexander Craig; Royal License proving ownership in light of French hostilities. (Purchase? 23 March 1950.)
- U.S. Revenue Cutter Rush, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  Weekly Reports of U.S. Revenue Cutter Rush for September 1838. (Gift from Robert Fridenburg, 1 July 1933.)
- U.S.S. St. Paul, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  Morning Reports of prisoners in the brig on the U.S.S. St. Paul, May-August 1898 (Gift of Chas. A. Butler, 11 November 1898.)
- Brig. Sally, 1792 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  [Photostat] Report of Manifest of the Cargo of the Brig Sally (of Philadelphia), Michael Alcon, Master, from the Port of St. Eustatius.
- Sloop Sally, 1796 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  Report of Manifest of the Cargo of Sloop Sally (of Baltimore), George Travis, Master, from Port of Tappahannock to Port of New York. (Purchased from Charles F. Heartman, 19 May 1931.)
- Steamer Sarah Sands, 1850 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  Joseph Wrigley's Book of voyage on Steamer Sarah Sands from Rio to San Francisco. (Gift of Thomas W. Streeter, October 1963?)
- Schuyler's Steam Tow Boat Line, 1847-1881 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  Corporate Documents relating to the Schuyler's Steam Tow Boat Line (Samuel Schuyler), including stock certificates, stock sales, and articles of association. Bills of sales of ships. Also certificate of incorporation and other documents related to the Express Propeller Line. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman, 29 September 1911.)
- Schooner Shepherdess. Oversize, 1811 (Box Oversize - Small, Folder -)
  Crew List (Role D'Equipage) for Schooner Shepherdess, Daniel Hull Master. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman, 16 October 1923.)
- Ship Sincerity, 1810 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  Bill of Lading for Ship Sincerity, Master John Tatem, from Port of Christianstade bound for Philadelphia.
- U.S.S. Somers, 1842, 1846 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  Correspondence of John F. Steele to Father regarding loss of U.S. Brig Somers and 39 men off the Coast of Vera Cruz, 1846. (From the Naval History Society collection.) Correspondence of Findlay Schenck to sister, Elizabeth, regarding foiled mutiny upon U.S.S. Somers, 1842. (Gift from the Historical and Philosophical Society of Ohio, 30 November 1962.)
- Brig. Somerset, 1794 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  Insurance Policy covering vessel and cargo of Brig Somerset, Henry Rogers, Master on voyage to Kingston, Jamaica and return. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman, 24 April 1909.)
- Brig. Speedwell, 1784 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  Invoice of Sundries Shipped on board Brig Speedwell, Captain Welch, Bound from New York to Barbados. (Purchase?)
- Schooner Star, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  Bill of Lading for Schooner Star bound from Philadelphia to Providence. (Gift of Thomas Ollive Mabbott, 8 May 1942.)
- Brig. Susanna, 1788 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Insurance Policy covering vessel and cargo of Brig Susanna, Hugh Stocker, Master, for 12 month period. (Purchase, 20 September 1923.)
- Ship Teaplant, 1812 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  Entry of Teas Imported by Edmund Fanning in the Ship Teaplant, Peter Murphy Master, from Canton.
- Brig. Thule, 1825-1826 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Survey of Damage by Dock Wardens of Brig Thule, Captain Sullivan, from Carnarven, Wales. (Gift? of Roger Butterfield, July 1979.)
- Ship Titanic, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Correspondence of Walford Brothers, London to R. Lyman, Esq. regarding shipped items that may have gone down with the Titanic. (Gift from Susan E. Lyman, in memory of her father Robert Hunt Lyman, 9 September 1941.)
- Port of Troy, New York, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Surveyor Certificate of Canal and River Boat Wrecker No. 2. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman?, 5 December 1923.)
- Steamer Virginia, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Bill of Lading of Steamer Virginia, Master Seal, bound from Philadelphia to Richmond. (Gift from Thomas Ollive Mabbott, 24 June 1938.)
- U.S. Revenue Cutter Washington, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Weekly Reports of U.S. Revenue Cutter Washington for November and December 1839. (Gift from Robert Fridenburg, 1 July 1933.)
- Ship Washington, 1799 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  Bill of Lading of Ship Washington, James J. Coffin, Master, bound from New York to Liverpool. Receipt of payment United States Revenue Boat; Collector of Customs for the District of Salem (1847).
- Schooner The William. Oversize, 1809 (Box Oversize - Small, Folder -)
  Presidential permission (James Madison) for Schooner The William and Master John Valentine bound from New York to St. Bartholomew to depart. Multi-lingual form. Contains Presidential signature. (Gift from George A. Zabriskie, 4 March 1947.)
- Brig. Windmill, 1762 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  Correspondence of Gerard Beekman to Mr. Christopher Champlin (Merchant of Rhode Island) regarding Insurance for voyage of Brig Windmill, George Crosswell, Master, bound from Rhode Island to The Cape.
- Various Ships ("Hudson River Ships"), 1837-1882 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  Bills of Lading for ships lying in the port of Eddyville, Rondout, N.Y. and bound for various cities, bearing cement from the Newark and Rosendale Lime & Cement Co.: Barge Tupper, Barge Samuel Cox, Barge Mary, Sloop Liberator, Sloop Ransom, Sloop Ambassador, Sloop Mammouth, Sloop Index, Sloop Lafayette, Sloop Y.W. Jacobs, Sloop Franklin, Sloop Shepherdess, Boat 363, Boat New Jersey of Eddyville, Boat Hellen, Boat L.A. Sikis, Boat Amos Stacey, Schooner Celeste, Schooner E.M. Bransconi, and Schooner Lauretta. (Gift from Samuel V. Hoffman, 5 December 1923.)
- Various Ships (Import Certifications), 1820, 1822, 1825, 1827-1828 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Includes import certifications from the Port of New-York for the ships Superb (Ayman, Master, from Bermuda with Jamaica rum), China (Dowdall, Master, from Canton with Hyson tea), Ajax (Dowdall, Master, from Canton with Bohea tea), Maria (Evans, Master, from Canton with tea), Mary Lord (Ansley, Master, from Canton with Bohea tea), Superior (Dowdall, Master, from Canton with gunpowder tea). (Many stamped as from the Harrold E. Gillingham Collection, 14 January 1937).
- Various Ships: Brig. Industry, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bills of Lading, Peter William Marrennes
- Various Ships: Sloop Philander, Sloop Appollo, Sloop Nancy, Sloop Ontario, Sloop Armenian, New Sloop, 1809-1815 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Sundries delivered to Burnell Brown
- Various Ships: Sloop Sublyme, Sloop Invincible, Sloop Undaunted, Sloop Ontario, Sloop Ann Mariah, 1811-1816 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Proof of ownership
- Various Ships: Schooner Eliza, 1813 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Invoices: James Colson (New Haven), William S. Hotchkiss (New Haven), John McNeil (New Canaan)
- Various Ships: Schooner Weasel, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Receipt for payment for services, Jas. Richardson
- Various Ships: Sloop Experiment, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Promissary Note, John Casenave
- Various Ships: Sloop Augusta, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Invoice, Mr. John Farrell Thompson
- Various Ships: Sloop Ducator, 1815 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Various Ships: Brig. Maria Francisca, 1816 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bill of Lading, Charles Dickinson. Invoice, W. Thompson.
- Various Ships: Sloop Speculation, 1816-1818 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Invoice, Tucker & Carter
- Various Ships: Schooner Echo of Savannah, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Wharfage Bill
- Various Ships: Brig. Stoughton, 1818 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Portage Bill, Voyage to/from Guadalupe. Invoice, William Reese. Bills of Lading: N. Monteverde, Samuel G. Ogden. J.P. Durand (in French)
- Various Ships: Sloop Neptune, 1824 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Testimony in the case of Sloop Neptune, which sank on 24 November 1824.
- Various Ships: Sloop Victory, 1840-1861 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Invoices: William Thorp, Hiram Hanmore, H. Hughs, E. Goodwin (Sail Maker), Charles Harriman (Ship Chandler), John R. Cochran, Hamilton Biggam (Ship Chandler), Benjamin Bennett (Sail Maker), blacksmith. Wharfage bills, towing bill.
- Various Ships: Ship Saracen, 1845-1848 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Correspondence and Account Statement, Reid & Murray (Glasgow), Captain N.T. Hawkins
- Various Ships: Steamboat Chelsea, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Weekly Amount of Ferriage for week ending 2 July 1853.
- Various Ships: Steamer Mazeppa, 1856 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Invoice, J.M. Holt
- Various Ships: Steamer Estrella, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Letter of instruction from Messrs. Sean & Sintz to Capt. J.T. Morrill.
- Various Ships: Harriet L. Young Charter, 1866 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bill of Lading for cement
- Various Ships: Canal Boat R.P. Boardwell, 1868 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Statement of Trip
- Various Ships: No Ship, 1848 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  City of New York Certificate appointing Joseph Hasbrouk to Inspector of Customs
- Various Ships: No Ship, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bill of Lading, United States Express Company, John K. Perry
- Various Ships: No Ship, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bill of Lading, Ulster & Delaware Railroad Co.
- Various Ships: No Ship, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Bill of Lading, Stony Clove and Catskill Mountain Railroad Co.